PARASITE
PASOŻYT
In the end, no one knows what they really are.
Nikt nie wiem, czym one tak naprawdę były.
They're still being talked about online,
Żadna agencja publiczna nie wydała oficjalnego oświadczenia.
Ever since the battle at the city hall,
Po walkach w ratuszu
there's been no notable parasite activity in this area
nie zauważono już aktywności pasożytów w tym obszarze,
or even in the whole world.
ani w ogóle na całym świecie.
Why did they suddenly go quiet?
Dlaczego tak ucichły?
One obvious reason was that the battle was effective as an object lesson.
Jednym z powodów mogło być to, że po prostu dostały nauczkę.
Another was that they, themselves,
Innym to,
became even more adept at blending into human society.
że nauczyły się lepiej wtapiać w otoczenie.
Like Tamura Reiko before them, some gradually altered their diet
Wzięły przykład z Tamury Reiko i zaczęły modyfikować swą dietę,
to require less human flesh and thus become more human.
żeby zmniejszyć swoje zapotrzebowanie na ludzkie mięso.
As for the one here…
A jeśli chodzi o tego tutaj…
Shinichi.
Shinichi.
Migi, you never change.
Migi, a ty znowu.
You're so blunt.
Jesteś nieokrzesany.
But I'm really glad you're alive, Migi.
Ale cieszę się, że żyjesz.
How do I look to you now, Shinichi?
Jak teraz dla ciebie wyglądam?
You look like you.
Wyglądasz jak ty.
Before, you were totally different.
Wcześniej byłeś zupełnie inny.
I think it was like…
Chyba jak…
Never mind.
Nieważne.
I've actually come here today to say goodbye.
Jestem tu, żeby się pożegnać.
What do you mean?
Jak to?
I think I'll go to sleep.
Zamierzam zasnąć.
Sleep?
Zasnąć?
You're always going to sleep anyway.
Ty cały czas śpisz.
It's a different kind of sleep.
Tym razem będzie inaczej.
This time, it'll be for a while longer.
Tym razem pośpię trochę dłużej.
It may very well last until I die.
Być może nawet do śmierci.
In other words,
Pomyśl o tym tak,
you can think of it as regaining an ordinary right hand.
że odzyskujesz władzę nad prawą ręką.
What? What are you talking about?
Co ty gadasz?
I don't get what you mean!
Nie rozumiem.
My internal structure has been altered yet again.
Moja struktura wewnętrzna znowu się zmieniła.
In particular, my time spent in a lucid dream of sorts within Gotou's body,
Będąc w ciele Gotou, doznałem świadomego snu
where I felt alone yet not alone, has been a major factor in that change.
i czułem, że jestem sam, ale nie samotny. Między innymi to wywołało zmianę.
But Migi.
Ale, Migi…
Not only did I obtain a massive amount of information at once
Nie tylko przyjąłem ogromną ilość informacji,
but I also became capable of pursuing many lines of thought in parallel.
ale i byłem w stanie snuć wiele wątków myślowych na raz.
I now want to shut out all other information for a while
Chcę odciąć przypływ informacji
and see what I can accomplish with the material
i zobaczyć, co mogę osiągnąć z tymi, które już posiadam.
So, I will stop all surface activity for the time being.
Z tego powodu przerwę zewnętrzną aktywność.
What? I can't believe I'm hearing this.
Co? Nie mogę w to uwierzyć.
You were always so curious.
Zawsze byłeś taki ciekawy świata.
What's wrong?
Co się stało?
Aren't there still all kinds of things you don't know?
Wciąż nie wiesz tylu rzeczy.
You're right.
Masz rację.
Well, I'll put it this way.
Ujmijmy to tak:
I'm going to try heading in a different direction.
zamierzam udać się w innym kierunku.
A direction that's slightly different from your world.
W kierunku, który różni się nieco od twojego świata.
I don't understand.
Nie rozumiem.
Shinichi, I want you to think of me as a dream.
Shinichi, chcę, żebyś myślał o mnie jak o śnie.
That's why I'm saying goodbye to you in one.
Dlatego też żegnam się w nim z tobą.
What are you talking about?
O czym ty mówisz?
All the days I spent with you, all the times we helped each other,
Spędziliśmy razem tyle czasu, pomagaliśmy sobie –
they weren't a dream!
to nie był sen!
You're right.
Masz rację.
The horrific events in your vicinity,
Te okropieństwa, jakie działy się wokół ciebie,
the deaths of many people, did happen in reality.
ta śmierć, to działo się naprawdę.
Mom!
Mama!
Why is Mom here?
Co ona tu robi?
It's a mental projection you generated upon hearing me talk about deaths.
Przywołałeś ten obraz, słysząc, jak mówię o śmierci.
Oh, so this is how your mother appears to you in your mind.
A więc tak widzisz swoją matkę.
What?
Co?
What do you mean?
O czym ty mówisz?
What's this?
Co to?
They're all very different from how I perceived them in my mind's eye.
Ja wyobrażam sobie te osoby zupełnie inaczej.
Show how you see me.
A jak spostrzegasz mnie?
What do you mean, "huh"?
O co chodzi?
Well, so that's that.
No proszę.
We can pretty much only hope to understand each other on certain points.
W niektórych kwestiach możemy tylko próbować się zrozumieć.
Even supposing that humans, who technically share the same structure,
Choć ludzie są zbudowani z tych samych elementów,
could exchange souls with each other,
gdyby mogli wymieniać się świadomością,
they would see and hear worlds far beyond their imagination.
poznaliby niewyobrażalne rzeczy.
Well, I should get going.
Pora już na mnie.
I'm going to flip the switch.
Wyłączam się.
Wait! How am I supposed to fight parasites by myself, if they show up?
A jeśli wrócą pasożyty? Jak mam z nimi walczyć?
You'll be fine.
Poradzisz sobie.
You should be more wary of traffic accidents.
Tylko uważaj na drodze.
Wait!
Czekaj!
So I can't ever talk to you again?
Więc już nigdy nie będę mógł z tobą porozmawiać?
Possibly.
Być może.
But well, it's not like either of us is going to die anytime soon.
Choć żaden z nas nie umrze raczej w najbliższym czasie.
Besides, it's not normal for someone to talk to his hand, anyway.
Zresztą kto to widział, żeby gadać do własnej ręki?
This is too much.
Jak możesz tak to na mnie zrzucać?
You'll have forgotten all about this dream when you wake up, like usual.
Kiedy się obudzisz, zapomnisz ten sen, jak zwykle.
I'd like you to have forgotten about me along with this dream.
Chciałbym, żebyś tak samo zapomniał o mnie.
Yes, I'm sure you can.
Z pewnością możesz zapomnieć.
Listen, when you wake up in the morning,
Kiedy się obudzisz, zobaczysz już tylko zwykłą prawą rękę.
That's how things should be.
I tak powinno być.
Migi.
Migi.
Thank you for everything, Shinichi.
Dziękuję za wszystko, Shinichi.
There's no way I could forget!
Jak mógłbym cię zapomnieć?
Idiot!
Ty kretynie!
You idiot.
Ty głupku.
Nagai's been annoying lately, always following me around.
Wkurza mnie ten Nagai. Ciągle za mną łazi.
Oh, Akiho.
Ech, Akiho.
Oh, there he is!
To on.
Izumi-kun, long time no see!
Dawno się nie widzieliśmy.
Hey. Did you wait long?
Długo czekałaś?
No, Yuuko and Akiho just happened to pass by.
Nie. Akurat wpadłam na Yuuko i Akiho.
I'm going to an art exhibit with Akiho.
Idę do galerii sztuki z Akiho.
Not that I really want to.
Choć ja tam mam to w nosie.
We wouldn't want to be in your way, so we'll take off.
Nie będziemy wam przeszkadzać.
Later, guys!
Na razie!
They seem to be having fun.
Są w dobrym nastroju.
Yeah, looks like they're enjoying college life to the fullest.
Wygląda na to, że dobrze im na studiach.
I've been left behind.
Zostałem z tyłu.
Hurry up and catch up, then.
No to spiesz się i dołącz.
I'm waiting for you.
Czekam na ciebie.
Studying after failing college entrance exams
Nauka do egzaminów na studia
is like taking a nap in a park on a sunny day
jest jak drzemka w parku w słoneczny dzień
compared to all the crazy stuff that came before.
w porównaniu do tego, co już przeżyłem.
Nothing's happened lately.
Nic się ostatnio nie dzieje.
I haven't come across a single sign of the parasites around here.
Nie zauważyłem ani jednego śladu pasożytów.
I talked about what might've happened to them
Rozmawiałem przez telefon z Udą
with Uda-san in Izu over the phone, once,
o tym, co się mogło z nimi stać.
but I didn't tell him about Migi.
Ale nie powiedziałem mu o Migim.
Migi's "disappearance" is unique, even among his kind.
Jego zniknięcie było czymś wyjątkowym, nawet wśród pasożytów.
Migi, in the end, I never did understand you.
Migi, nigdy do końca cię nie rozumiałem.
But that's okay.
Ale to nic.
I'm sure you're walking in places unknown to me.
Teraz eksplorujesz nieznane mi światy.
The many battles we fought together,
Walki, które razem toczyliśmy,
they weren't for the sake of Earth or anything.
nie miały służyć Ziemi,
It was for humanity.
ale ludzkości.
Or, really, more for me as an individual.
A może po prostu mnie.
In the end,
Nie wiem, jak wyglądało to z perspektywy pasożytów,
Of course not.
Oczywiście.
It wasn't possible from the beginning.
To nigdy nie było możliwe.
As two different species,
Jako dwa różne gatunki
we may at times take advantage of each other and kill each other,
możemy służyć sobie nawzajem albo się zabijać,
but it's impossible to understand each other.
ale nigdy się nie zrozumiemy.
Actually, you shouldn't even think that you've figured out
Nie możesz pojąć innego gatunku na podstawie własnego rozumowania.
I think it's human arrogance to think we understand how other life forms feel.
Ludzie są aroganccy, myśląc, że rozumieją, co czują inne formy życia.
There may be no other life forms that are truly a "friend" to man.
Być może żaden inny gatunek nie może być przyjacielem ludzkości.
Still, even if we can't comprehend them,
Jednak choć nie potrafimy ich zrozumieć,
We protect other species because humans themselves are lonely creatures.
Chronimy inne gatunki, ponieważ jesteśmy samotnymi stworzeniami.
We protect the environment because humans themselves don't want to go extinct.
Chronimy środowisko, ponieważ nie chcemy wyginąć.
What drives us is simply self-gratification.
Kieruje nami egoizm.
But I think that's fine and that it's really all there is to it.
Ale myślę, że nie ma w tym nic złego.
There's no point in despising humans by human standards.
Nie możemy potępiać ludzi na podstawie ludzkich wartości.
That's right.
Tak.
So, in the end,
Myślę więc,
it's hypocritical for us to love Earth without loving ourselves.
że nie możemy kochać Ziemi, nie kochając samych siebie.
What's with you?
Co z tobą?
Oh, just…
Ja tylko myślałem sobie, jak tu ostatnio jest spokojnie.
Really?
Tak?
I heard crime's on the rise.
A jednak jest coraz więcej przestępstw.
That's it!
To jest to.
That's why they're no longer conspicuous.
Dlatego już się nie wyróżniają.
Well, maybe they never were conspicuous to begin with.
W sumie to nigdy się tak nie wyróżniały.
Even murders can be chalked up to wild beasts feeding themselves.
Nawet morderstwa mogły zostać potraktowane jak ataki dzikich zwierząt.
In a narrow sense, they were our enemies,
Byliśmy sobie wrogami,
but in a broader sense, they were our kindred.
ale w szerszym sensie byliśmy sobie pokrewni.
All of us were born here, on this planet, weren't we?
Wszyscy urodziliśmy się na tej planecie.
And we've been living our lives close to someone else.
I wiedliśmy życie blisko kogoś innego.
PARASYTE
PASOŻYT
Come to think of it,
Myślę sobie,
we've been together for a while, haven't we?
że długo już ze sobą chodzimy.
We're together?
To my ze sobą chodzimy?
Just kidding.
Tylko żartuję.
Hey.
Hej.
I forgot what I was about to say.
Zapomniałem, co chciałem powiedzieć.
What?
Co?
What now?
Co znowu?
Was I imagining it?
Zdawało mi się?
He looked like that guy.
Wyglądał jak on.
No, I thought I saw someone I knew.
Myślałem, że zobaczyłem znajomego.
NO MOTOR VEHICLES - PEDESTRIANS ONLY BICYCLES AND APPROVED, VEHICLES ALLOWED
ZAKAZ DLA POJAZDÓW SILNIKOWYCH
No, it is him!
Nie, to naprawdę on!
-What's wrong? -Can you hold this?
- Co jest? - Potrzymaj to.
Wait here.
Poczekaj tu.
I'll be right back!
Zaraz wrócę.
He went through here?
Poszedł tędy?
Is he looking for someone?
Szuka kogoś?
He's looking for me.
Szuka mnie.
Yo.
Hej.
Satomi!
Satomi!
What the…
Co…
What the hell?
Co jest? To nie może się dziać!
I should've just pretended I didn't see him!
Mogłem udawać, że go nie widzę.
Let's go.
Chodźmy.
Hey, what are you--
Hej, co ty…?
Someone, help!
Pomocy!
I won't kill you until later.
Ciebie zabiję później. Najpierw muszę pogadać z twoim chłopakiem.
Satomi!
Satomi!
Hey.
Hej.
You didn't waste any time, huh?
Nie marnujesz czasu, co?
Satomi!
Satomi!
Izumi-kun.
Izumi-kun.
How cute.
Jak uroczo.
She's so scared, she can barely talk.
Strach niemal odebrał jej mowę.
Don't! What did you do to her?
Co jej zrobiłeś?
Nothing yet.
Jeszcze nic.
The blood's from that broad.
To krew tamtej panienki.
Hey, come on.
Co ty.
Can you let her go?
Nie możesz jej puścić?
Are you stupid?
Zgłupiałeś?
Then, what do I need to do?
Co mam zrobić?
If you'll spare her life,
Zrobię wszystko, żebyś darował jej życie.
Is there something you want?
Chcesz czegoś?
Please tell me what it is.
Tylko powiedz.
What do I want?
Czego chcę?
The cops aren't stupid.
Gliniarze nie są głupi.
It's only a matter of time before I'll be hanged.
Powieszą mnie prędzej czy później.
But since I managed to run into you first,
Ale jako że wpadłem na ciebie,
I thought I'd ask for an answer that wouldn't come from a human.
chcę usłyszeć odpowiedź od kogoś, kto nie jest człowiekiem.
It makes sense when monsters kill humans.
Gdy potwory zabijają ludzi, ma to dla nas sens.
They're just feeding themselves.
One po prostu się żywią.
But what about me? What do you think I am?
A ja? Czym według ciebie jestem?
Nah, I think you know the answer already.
Myślę, że już znasz odpowiedź.
You know I'm the true human here.
Wiesz, że jestem najprawdziwszym człowiekiem.
Why are other guys so much better at keeping themselves in control?
Inne zwierzęta potrafią o wiele lepiej kontrolować swoją liczebność.
It's human nature to want to kill each other, you know?
Zabijanie się nawzajem leży w ludzkiej naturze.
They're making a big fuss about nothing
Ludzie oburzają się morderstwem,
when they're all bloodthirsty themselves.
kiedy sami są żądni krwi.
People who don't know who they truly are bitch at me about what I do,
Ludzie, którzy nie wiedzą, kim naprawdę są, demonizują mnie,
but I can tell monsters and humans apart just by looking at them.
ale ja potrafię odróżniać potwory od ludzi, tylko na nich patrząc.
I know how unnatural this whole world's become, too.
Wiem, jak bardzo odeszliśmy od natury.
There's no need for monsters!
Nie potrzebujemy potworów.
Humans were created to be cannibals in the first place!
Ludzie mają zaprogramowany kanibalizm.
We've been like that for thousands of years!
Byliśmy tacy tysiące lat.
It's because we tried to stop all of a sudden
Zmieniliśmy się, a przez to zrobiły się nas miliardy.
The world's going to burst if we don't do something!
Świat pęknie, jeśli czegoś nie zrobimy.
Everyone's a damn liar, but you're different, right?
Wszyscy kłamią, ale ty jesteś inny, prawda?
Be honest, like me.
Bądź szczery, jak ja.
What are you getting at?
Do czego zmierzasz?
Don't play dumb.
Nie udawaj głupka.
You're a mixed breed, aren't you? You've got monster in you!
Wiem, że masz w sobie potwora.
What?
Co?
I knew from the first time I laid eyes on you.
Od razu go w tobie dostrzegłem.
It's not in your head, though.
Ale nie w głowie.
-It's somewhere else in your body. -Don't…
Gdzie indziej w ciele.
Don't be ridiculous!
Nie bądź śmieszny.
You're his girlfriend.
Jesteś jego dziewczyną.
You must've seen his body.
Widziałaś jego ciało.
Wasn't there some suspicious mark
Nie ma jakichś podejrzanych blizn,
that might've been where a monster burrowed inside?
przez które mógł wpełznąć potwór?
Please.
Proszę.
Let her go.
Puść ją.
Answer me!
Odpowiedz mi!
I'm the normal human being, right?
To ja jestem tu normalnym człowiekiem, prawda?
I'm just following my instincts!
Słucham instynktu!
I'm the one being true to my nature,
Żyję w zgodzie z moją naturą,
but human society is desperate to keep ignoring me.
ale społeczeństwo wciąż spycha mnie na margines.
I'm just asking you for a favor,
Pytam cię o to,
given that you're halfway between humans and monsters.
ponieważ jesteś w połowie drogi między ludźmi a potworami.
Izumi-kun.
Izumi-kun.
Halfway between humans and parasites, huh?
W połowie drogi między ludźmi a potworami?
Someone said something similar to me before.
Ktoś powiedział mi kiedyś coś podobnego.
Compared to Gotou, you're spun glass,
W porównaniu do Gotou jesteś słabeuszem,
but I'm not that strong anymore.
ale ja nie jestem już taki silny.
If words are all you want, I'll say anything.
Powiem cokolwiek, jeśli możemy załatwić to słowami.
Yeah, you're right!
Tak, masz rację!
Like you said, I'm--
Dobrze powiedziałeś…
Izumi-kun!
Izumi-kun!
Call the police.
Wezwij policję.
You don't need to listen to this jerk.
Nie musisz go wysłuchiwać.
How can he be considered a normal human being?
Jak on może uważać się za normalnego człowieka?
You're even worse than those monsters!
Jesteś nawet gorszy niż te potwory!
You were so scared, you couldn't even talk,
A jeszcze przed chwilą bałaś się tak, że nie mogłaś mówić.
I'm not scared of you!
Nie boję się ciebie!
I've been through much worse at school!
W szkole przeżyłam o wiele gorsze rzeczy!
Satomi.
Satomi.
Both Izumi-kun and I have gone through it.
Izumi-kun też przeszedł tak wiele.
That's right. Izumi-kun, you were amazing when it all happened.
Izumi-kun, byłeś taki wspaniały.
You carried me and protected me with everything you had.
Chroniłeś mnie całym sobą.
Sure, you might not be "normal",
Może i nie jesteś jak inni, ale jesteś człowiekiem.
Humans think all life is precious!
Dla ludzi każde życie jest święte!
You're the monster, jerk!
To on jest potworem.
That's enough, Satomi.
Przestań, Satomi.
Izumi-kun, just go!
Izumi-kun, po prostu odejdź.
Sure, fine.
Jasne, leć po gliny, młody.
I think this girl's going to be more fun.
A ja tymczasem rozbiorę tę zabaweczkę na kawałki.
This will probably be the last fun I ever have.
To będzie moja ostatnia rozrywka.
It's always more fun taking apart the spunky ones.
Z pyskatymi panienkami zawsze jest lepsza zabawa.
Shinichi-kun!
Shinichi-kun.
I…
Zawsze próbowałam za tobą nadążyć.
But you're so fast,
Ale jesteś taki szybki i przenosisz się do światów, których nie rozumiem.
I was the one left behind.
To ja zawsze zostawałam z tyłu.
But now that I've finally caught up with you,
Teraz, gdy wreszcie cię dogoniłam,
it looks like I might've actually gone too far ahead.
mogłam zrobić o krok za daleko.
Stop!
Nie!
I'll save her! I'll get to her in time!
Uratuję ją! Dobiegnę na czas!
That's right, I'm fast!
Tak, jestem szybki! Nie jestem zwyczajnym człowiekiem!
To me, he looks like he's frozen in time!
Czas płynie dla mnie wolniej.
With my left, strike his knife hand up
Wytrącam mu nóż lewą ręką
and slam his jaw!
i uderzam w szczękę!
Then, with my right…
A prawą…
Toys are so easily broken.
Zabawki są takie kruche.
No. It can't be.
Nie. Tylko nie to.
This is too much.
Tylko nie to.
Why does it always end like this?
Czemu to zawsze się tak kończy?
An organism I met in passing and got to know
Organizm, który miałem okazję poznać,
was suddenly dead.
nagle umarł.
Why do I get sad when that happens?
Czemu zawsze mnie to tak smuci?
Well, that's because humans have so much time on their hands.
Ponieważ ludzie mają zbyt dużo wolnego czasu.
But that's their greatest merit.
Ale to ich największa cnota.
An organism with time to spare in their hearts,
Organizm z wolnym czasem i otwartym sercem
how wonderful is that?
to coś wspaniałego.
So, quit whining already.
Więc przestań marudzić.
I'm getting tired, so you can do the holding.
Tracę siłę. Złap ją sam.
Satomi!
Satomi!
I got to her in time?
Zdążyłem?
You okay?
Nic ci nie jest?
Thanks, Migi.
Dziękuję, Migi.
You're still alive!
Ty wciąż żyjesz!
Did Satomi see Migi?
Czy Satomi widziała Migiego?
Oh, well.
No cóż.
I don't mind if she saw him.
Nie mam nic przeciwko.
What a beautiful sky.
Piękne niebo.
Do you remember the puppy that died?
Pamiętasz tego szczeniaczka? Kiedy umarł, wyrzuciłem go na śmietnik.
I forgot to tell you before,
Zapomniałem ci powiedzieć,
but after I thought about it for a while,
ale po jakimś czasie wróciłem i zakopałem go pod drzewem.
I know.
Wiem.
You did that because you're…
Zrobiłeś to, bo jesteś…
You're Shinichi-kun.
Jesteś Shinichi-kun.
There are three people on the ground there, too!
Tu są trzy ciała!
Three, he says.
Trzy?
Yeah, they think we're dead.
Myślą, że nie żyjemy.
We were all born here on Earth.
Wszyscy urodziliśmy się na Ziemi.
We try to keep understanding each other along these tiny points
Powoli próbujemy zrozumieć się nawzajem.
We try to get closer to someone else
Póki trwa nasze życie, próbujemy zbliżyć się do siebie.